Guide to the Truman A. Warner Papers MS 026
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
- Series II: Manuscript
  - Later Chapters
    - Green Family Business, 1964-1986 (Box 39, Folder 20)
      Articles include factory fire and obituaries.
    - Beckerle & Co. (Schuldice/Fay/Peix), 1894-1984 (Box 39, Folder 21)
      Research notes and genealogy of Joseph F. Shuldice.
    - F. H. Lee Family and Business, 1937-1988 (Box 39, Folder 22)
      Research notes on downsizing, factory fires, family genealogy, and transcript of talk to shop foreman and management by Harold Rupp on ladies hat manufacture (1950-1951).
    - Mallory Family and Business, 1829-1996 (Box 39, Folder 23)
      Research notes and articles on fire/arson, genealogy, obituaries, Scott Fanton, and Ezra Mallory House.
    - McLachlan Family, 1950-1970 (Box 39, Folder 24)
      Research notes, articles on genealogy, business, and obituaries.
    - Francis - History of the Hatting Trade in Danbury, Conn 1860, 1856-1860 (Box 39, Folder 25)
    - Hatters/Rolls, 1792-1987 (Box 39, Folder 26)
      Research notes, book references, and articles on hatters during 1892-1906, the industry, apprenticeship, craft identities and skills.
    - Dun & Bradstreet, 1840-1890 (Box 39, Folder 27)
      Research notes from Harvard Business School Archives on Fairfield County and Tweedy Manufacturing Company.
    - Warner & Janick Hatting Paper, 1988 (Box 39, Folder 28)
      Research paper: Danbury Crowned Them All: The Rise and Fall of the Hatting Industry in Danbury, Connecticut by Truman Warner and Herbert Janick given at a conference at Eastern Connecticut State University on April 7, 1988.
    - Labor - Pessen Essay, 1983 (Box 39, Folder 29)
      Copy of Builders of the Young Republic by Edward Pessen, (1976).
    - Mercury Poisoning, 1967-1996 (Box 39, Folder 30)
      Newspaper articles on Dr. Alice Hamilton, industrial toxicologist. See also Student Research Papers #121: Mercurial Poisoning in the Hatters Fur-Cutting by Ruth Hobson; "Work, Health and Community: Danbury Connecticut's Struggle with an Industrial Disease." Labor's Heritage July 1990 (copy).
    - Frank - Hard Times in Hat Town, 1981 (Box 39, Folder 31)
      Research paper: Hard Times in Hat Towns: The Danbury Lockout of 1893-94 by David Montgomery (Yale University).
    - The Felt Hat Industry in the United States, undated (Box 39, Folder 32-37)
      Thesis by Edwin M. Benedict, Syracuse University.
    - Danbury Hatters Case, 1901-1990 (Box 39, Folder 38)
      Research notes and clippings. See also Student Research Papers: #123: The Sherman Anti-Trust Act in the Danbury Hatters Case by Eugene Nahley. #289: The Illegality of the Boycott by G. Kulhay. 1968. #311: The Danbury Hatters Case by C. R. Mann. #312: The Danbury Hatters Case: A Closer View by J. C. Sikora..
    - Hat Structures, 1927-1996 (Box 39, Folder 39)
      Research note and clippings on hat factories, demolition and fires.
    - Hatting - Bethel, 1963-1964 (Box 39, Folder 40)
      History of the hatting industry in Bethel.
    - Marketing of Hats, 1802-1971 (Box 39, Folder 41)
      Research notes on middle men and hatting entrepreneurs during the 19th century.
    - Hat Related Industries, 1824-1995 (Box 39, Folder 42)
      Research notes and clippings on the Turner Machine Company's hatting techniques.
    - Hatting - 1850-1980s, 1851-1982 (Box 39, Folder 43-44)
      Research notes and articles on social events, parades, people, and influence in the Danbury area.
    - Hatting in Danbury, 1954 (Box 39, Folder 45)
      Student paper: Hatting in Danbury: A brief historical report of the manufactures, the making of hats, and labor's role in the hatting industry of this community by L. Prushansky, New York University.
    - Hatting Decline, 1950-1994 (Box 39, Folder 46-48)
      Clippings and student papers: The Decline of the Hatting Industry and the Lee Company in Danbury, Connecticut by L. A. Tasheiko, and The Decline in the Hatting Industry, Danbury, Connecticut, 1940 - 1965 by G. F. O'Brien. Banking
    - Savings & Loans, 1958-1990 (Box 39, Folder 49)
      Articles on the expansion and demise in the 1980's.
    - Fleet/Shawmut, 1995-1996 (Box 39, Folder 50)
      Articles on mergers and downsizing.
    - Peoples Bank, 1990-1996 (Box 39, Folder 51)
      Articles on mortgage incentives and new marketing techniques.
    - City National Bank and Trust, 1948-1996 (Box 39, Folder 52)
      Articles on the history, employees, and mergers.
    - Banks - General History, 1824-1903 (Box 39, Folder 53)
      Research notes on area banks and copy of article in Connecticut Magazine, Vol. VIII. No. 1, June 1903 "The Financial History of Danbury" by Edward B. Beaton.
    - Bank Takeovers/Consolidations/Mergers, 1995 (Box 39, Folder 54)
      Clippings concerning the above.
    - Danbury National/Fairfield County Trust/Union Trust/First Fidelity/First Union, 1958-1996 (Box 39, Folder 55)
      Research notes and articles on data processing and on-line banking.
    - Banking Technologies, 1964-1996 (Box 39, Folder 56)
      Planning and construction of data processing, banking by computer, computer, ATMs, competition and mergers.
    - Union Savings Bank, 1961-1996 (Box 39, Folder 57-58)
      Articles on modernizing and enlarging business in the area, and Annual Reports (1982-1983, 1985, 1994).
    - Savings Bank of Danbury, 1849-1996 (Box 39, Folder 59)
      Articles on Ives and the Danbury Bank. See also: Truman Warner Research Papers: Ives.
    - State National Bank, 1963-1978 (Box 39, Folder 60)
      Articles on employees and history of the bank. The First Hundred Years of the State National Bank of Connecticut, 1963- 1963.
    - Banks and Loan Companies, 1959-1996 (Box 39, Folder 61-62)
      Articles on troubled banks, mergers, interstate banking, Chase, Greenwood, and City Trust.
    - Banks, 1970-1997 (Box 39, Folder 63-65)
      Articles on banking activities, mergers and marketing strategies.
    - Economics, 1947-1996 (Box 39, Folder 66-69)
      Information on banking activities, financial cycles, mergers, and marketing strategies. Also included Economic Problems of thePost-War World by A. H. Hansen. See also: Truman Warner Research Papers: Danbury Business and Danbury Business and Economy.
- Series III: Personal Papers
  Nuclear energy - United States - History; Scott Fanton Museum and Historical Society; United States - History - 1939-1945; Danbury (Conn.) -- History.; Connecticut -- Centennial; Western Connecticut State University - History; Danbury Centennial; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States
  - 1. Early Childhood
    - Infancy, 1920-1952 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      Birth certificate, small pox vaccine, and Danbury News-Times clippings from January 7, 1920.
    - Early Childhood, 1920-1929 (Box 33, Folder 1-7)
      Two b/w photographs: "Truman and Louisa" and Truman with his mother. One b/w studio portrait of Warner, n.d. Booklets: Baby's Days and Nestle's Mother Book About the Care and Feeding of Babies. In addition, several letters, 28 postcards, and valentines from family and friends.
    - Early Childhood, 1920-1929 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      My First Scrapbook.
    - Ages 6-12+, 1926-1955 (Box 33, Folder 8)
      Correspondence, newspaper articles, two b/w photographs, and memorabilia.
    - Ages 6-12+, 1926-1955 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      My Chinese Book.
    - New York Times, Dec 8, 1929 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Westchester/Connecticut Picture Section. The Danbury Lions Club Minstrel Troup pictured at a benefit performance at the Danbury High School on November 25-26, 1929. Warner performed the Irish Jig along with other children. Program: Lions Minstrels, Danbury High School, November 25-26, 1929.
    - Lincoln Avenue Elementary School, 1927-1929 (Box 33, Folder 9)
      Report card, promotion card, class assignments.
    - Lincoln Avenue Elementary School, 1927-1929 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Drawings and class assignments
    - New Street Elementary School, 1929-1933 (Box 33, Folder 10-11)
      Assignment booklets, writings, certificates, and report cards.
    - New Street Elementary School, 1932 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Autograph book.
    - Bradley's Historical and Geographical Outline Map, No. XVII., undated (Box OS 4, Folder *)
    - Palmer Method Certificate of Business Writing, 1931 (Folder OS Folder 6)
    - Main Street School, 1931-1986 (Box 33, Folder 12-19)
      Memorabilia, map, programs, poems, certificates, copy of 1933 class photograph, copies of the student newspaper The Echo (1931-1932), Our State, 1635-1935 (student authored articles), and newspaper articles.
    - Main Street School, 1933 (Box 36, Folder 1-2)
      The Echo.
    - Main Street School, 1932, 1953 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Current Events, September 26-30, 1932 issue; and, Danbury News- Times, June 18, 1953, includes list of 48 honor students.
    - Newman's Dancing School, 1927-1939 (Box 36, Folder 3-4)
      Correspondence, programs, and clippings.
    - The New York Times February 6, 1927, undated (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Newspaper photograph. Members of the Newman Dancing School at their annual masquerade party.
    - Nolan Music Classes, 1930-1936 (Box 36, Folder 5)
      Concert and recital programs.
    - 12 to College, 1932-1942 (Box 33, Folder 20-21)
      Invitations, greeting cards, and assorted memorabilia.
    - Hi-Y Boy Scouts, 1934-1938 (Box 36, Folder 6)
      Fairfield County Young Men's Christian Association, programs, newspaper articles, Camp Mohawk, minutes from Hi-Y meetings.
    - High School, 1933-1977 (Box 36, Folder 7-14)
      School assignments/papers, photographs, correspondence, graduation programs/cards, Commercial Pathfinder (Danbury High School newspaper published by the commercial students) writings, newspaper articles, and 40th reunion for the class of 1937.
    - High School, 1934-1937 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Three graduation photographs, Chronicle=Rostrum 1934 (Danbury High School newspaper), and the following: 6 Tag Day tags (one contains autographs), and one 1937 Junior Prom dance card. Two small D.H.S. pennant, and one score card.
    - The Index of The Class of 1937, Danbury High School., undated (Box OS 4, Folder *)
    - Danbury State Teachers College, 1937-1944 (Box 33, Folder 22-26)
      Acceptance to DSTC, grades, course materials, correspondence, student handbooks, three color postcards, two 3x4 b/w photographs of Warner, graduation items, and Kappa Delta Pi membership cards.
    - Danbury State Teachers College, ca.1937-1941 (Box 33, Folder 27-28)
      Curriculum reading, course of study, practice schools, and speech of welcome.
    - Danbury State Teachers College, 1937-1953 (Box 33, Folder 29-35)
      Programs and invitations for commencements, plays, concerts, dinners, church events, annual dinners, and scripts for school productions.
    - Danbury State Teachers College, 1937-1977 (Box 36, Folder 15-16)
      Newspaper clippings on school events, faculty, speakers, graduation, etc.
    - Danbury State Teachers College, 1937-1941 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Dance cards for the following events: June Promenade - Class of 1938, June 18, 1937 Theta Iota Sorority Dance, June 29, 1937 Winter Formal, January 14, 1938 Spring Formal - Freshman Class, April 29, 1938 Junior-Senior Promenade, June 10, 1938 Fall Formal, October 6, 1938 Spring Formal - Class of 1942, April 14, 1939 Junior-Senior Promenade - Class of 1941, June 7, 1940 (2) June Formal - Senior Class, June 9, 1939 Stardust Formal - Student Council, March 7, 1941
    - Danbury State Teacher's College, 1990-1995 (Box 33, Folder 36)
      1940 class reunion. Correspondence, invitation and two 4x6 color photographs of 1940 class reunion.
    - Danbury State Teacher's College, 1979-1996 (Box 33, Folder 37-38)
      1941 class reunion. Correspondence, newsletters, flyers, commencement week schedule of events June 2-8, 1941, annual reunion picnic for the classes of 1940, 1941, and 1942.
    - Member List for the Class of 1941, 1996, undated (Box OS 7, Folder *)
    - Member List for the Class of 1935, 1991 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
    - Masters' Essays In History, 1933-1940 (Box 33, Folder 39-40)
      Instructions and suggestions for written work.
  - 2. Doctorate, Teachers College, Columbia University, 1955-1964
    These files consist mainly of Warner's field notes, handwritten and typed, written in English as well as Spanish, for his dissertation entitled School and Community in the Mezquital; A Case Study in Mexican Education.
    - Preliminary outline, undated (Box 33, Folder 41)
    - Outside Schools, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 42)
    - Kindergarten, 1955 (Box 33, Folder 43)
      Sketch of school building and surrounding area and instructions for education of preschoolers written in Spanish, Coca- Cola ad, and Direccion General de Educacion Pre Escolar, 1955.
    - Primary, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 44-45)
    - Education-General, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 46)
    - Research Notes, 1930-1932 (w/gaps), undated (Box 33, Folder 47)
    - Educational Materials (Spanish), undated (Box 33, Folder 48)
    - Daily Notes, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 49-54)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 33, Folder 55-60)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 33, Folder 61)
    - Research Notes (Spanish), undated (Box 33, Folder 62)
    - Dissertation (copy with noted revisions/missing pages), undated (Box 33, Folder 63-70)
      Field notes (12 small booklets of varying size)
    - Photographs (32 b/w of varying size), undated (Box 47, Folder 71)
    - An Elegy in a Country Churchyard. Scrapbook, undated (Box OS 4, Folder *)
  - 3. Central Christian Church
    - Church Activities, 1922-1994 (Box 47, Folder 72-76)
      Promotion cards, The Messenger, Certificates of Recognition, The Little Beginner, Beginners Lesson Stories, and Standard Cut Out Quarterly, tickets, plays, and newspaper articles.
    - Certificate of Recognition Lapel Pin, 1986 (Box OS 4, Folder *)
    - Church of Christ Bible School Cradle Roll Certificate, 1920 (Box OS 4, Folder *)
    - Church of Christ Bible School Cradle Roll Promotion Certificate, 1924 (Box OS 4, Folder *)
    - Beginner's Department Promotion Certificate, 1925 (Box OS 4, Folder *)
    - Teagarten, Miss Lyrel G., 1920-1988 (Box 36, Folder 17-18)
      Correspondence, newsletters, notes, cards, clippings chronicling Teagarten's life as a missionary posted to Luchoufu, Hofei, and Nantung, China, and Jamaica. See also: http://libweb.uoregon.edu/speccoll/guides/women/mission.html
    - Winnipesaukee, 1934-1939 (Box 33, Folder 77-80)
      Annual New England Young People's Summer Conferences. Correspondence, programs, three b/w 5 x 7 photographs (one mounted), and The Winnipesaukee Breeze.
    - The Young People's Union of the Church of Christ, 1934-1937 (Box 33, Folder 81)
      Programs, tickets, and clippings for the following plays: Billy's Bungalow (1934), A Regular Flirt (1935), I Will! I Won't! (1936), and Lady Spitfire (1937).
  - 4. Writings
    - My Life (ca. 1935) (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
      Warner family genealogy written in prose with photographs of family members. Cover filed separately in OS Box 2.
    - High School Essay, ca.1936-1938 (Box 34, Folder 3)
      No title.
    - The Danbury Library. 1938, ca.1938 (Box 34, Folder 4)
      Paper written for Library Technique course dated April 29, 1938.
    - Genealogy Through the Ages, 1930 (Box 34, Folder 5)
      Definition and origin of the word, and history from biblical days to the present time.
    - A Survey of the Mentally Ill in Connecticut, 1941 (Box 34, Folder 6)
      Research paper written by Truman Warner and Shirley H. Susnitsky for sociology course, dated January 1941.
    - Rhode Island Boundaries 1800, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 7)
      College research paper dated July 22, 1946.
    - Connecticut Tories 1776, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 8)
      College research paper dated August 1, 1946.
    - Prof. Robert Morris' Notes, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 9)
      Research notes and course outlines. See also: Truman Warner Personal Papers - Manuscript.
    - Review of The Growth of American Thought, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 10)
      College research paper dated August 12, 1946.
    - Review of The Cod Fisheries, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 11)
      College research paper dated July 29, 1946.
    - Review of Jeffery Amherst, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - American Revolution, 1946 (Box 34, Folder 13)
      College research paper (incomplete).
    - Joel Barlow and American Nationalism, 1947 (Box 34, Folder 14)
      College research paper dated January 15, 1947.
    - U. S. Constitution 1787-1789, Articles of Confederation, 1947 (Box 34, Folder 15)
      Research notes, bibliographies, and college research paper: Review of The Spirit of American Government, A Study of the Constitution: Its origin, Influence and Relation to Democracy dated April 23, 1947.
    - Anthropological Perspectives for Historians, 1974 (Box 34, Folder 16-17)
      A Presentation for the Fall Meeting of the Association for the Study of Connecticut History, November 9, 1974. Manchester Community College, Manchester, Connecticut.
    - Energy Systems and the Evolution of Connecticut Society, 1983 (Box 34, Folder 18)
      Written for the Center for Connecticut Studies, Eastern Connecticut State University. Condensed version of essay on Connecticut history.
    - MSS - News-Times Centennial Editions, 1983 (Box 34, Folder 19)
      Manuscript outline and revisions.
    - MSS - News-Times Centennial Editions, 1983 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Computer generated text: Danbury: The Past by T. Warner; and, Morgan vs. Danbury by William E. Devlin.
    - How Danbury Got To Be What It Is, Geography and Geology, 1985 (Box 34, Folder 20-24)
      Manuscript. Danbury Tricentennial Committee, Historic Booklet Series, No.4
    - Basic Overall Outline, undated (Box 34, Folder 25-28)
      Manuscript: How Danbury Got To Be What It Is, Geography and Geology.
    - How Danbury Got To Be What It Is, Geography and Geology, 1985 (Box 34, Folder 29)
      Danbury Tricentennial Committee, Historic Booklet Series, No.4
    - Focal Course, undated (Box 34, Folder 30-31)
      Manuscript for How Danbury Got To Be What It Is, Geography and Geology.
    - Danbury. Three Hundred Years of Change., 1985 (Box 34, Folder 32-34)
      Manuscript with revisions. Danbury Tricentennial Committee, Historic Booklet Series, No. 1.
    - Danbury. Three Hundred Years of Change., 1985 (Box 36, Folder 19-20)
      Manuscript with revisions. Danbury Tricentennial Committee, Historic Booklet Series, No.1.
    - Proposed Book-Basic Overall Outline, undated (Box 34, Folder 35)
      Handwritten notes on the settlement patterns and changing sources of energy for proposed book in collaboration with H. Janick and W. Devlin.
    - Proposed Book-Basic Structure of Book, undated (Box 34, Folder 36)
      Handwritten research notes for proposed book in collaboration with H. Janick and Bill Devlin.
    - Proposed Book-Research Notes, undated (Box 34, Folder 37-38)
  - 5. Teaching Career
    - Bethesda/Washington Trip, 1940 (Box 34, Folder 39)
      Correspondence with family.
    - Briarcliff High School, 1953 (Box 34, Folder *)
      Photograph of student class visiting Washington, D. C. (b/w 10 x 18)
    - Briarcliff High School, 1957 (Box 34, Folder 40-41)
      Study Guides for Essential Ideas Seminar. A Cooperative Experiment in Secondary Education.
    - Cooperstown Seminar, 1959-1969 (Box 36, Folder 21-22)
      Seminar on American Culture by the New York State Historical Association. Notes, programs, activities, pamphlets, and directory of participants.
    - Danbury State College (Closed), 1959-1969 (Box 34, Folder 42-43)
      Faculty investors.
    - Danbury State College (Closed), 1960-1966 (Box OS 4, Folder *)
    - Danbury State College/Alumni Scholarships (Closed), 1961-1966 (Box 34, Folder 44-45)
      Alumni Association Treasurer's Reports, information on the Perkins Memorial Fund and the Lothrop Davis Higgins Memorial Fund, and minutes of faculty meeting (1966).
    - Area Talks/Presentations, 1962-1994 (Box 36, Folder 23-26)
      Correspondence, invitations, programs, and newspaper clippings. Autographed letter to Warner from William P. Rogers dated March 4, 1970.
    - Dig We Must, Mexican Archaeology by Dr. Truman Warner., undated (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Poster: Talk sponsored by the Science Club.
    - Connecticut Bicentennial-TAW, 1971-1977 (Box 36, Folder 27-28)
      Correspondence and notes, newspaper articles, proposed program, and Parade Orders for the Danbury Bicentennial Parade of Patriots, July 4, 1976. Booklet: See also: Writings
    - Reading the Connecticut Landscape, 1978-1979 (Box 34, Folder 46)
      Summer course developed by Herb Janick and Truman Warner. Text of How Danbury Got To Be What It Is, Geography and Geology.
    - Danbury Tricentennial, 1983-1986 (Box 34, Folder 47)
      Scant number of letters, clippings, and twenty 3 ½ x 5 b/w images of the Danbury Tricentennial concert conducted by Leonard Bernstein at the Danbury Fairgrounds. See also: Writings.
    - ASCH/State Historical Societies, 1984-1987 (Box 34, Folder 48)
      Correspondence, 1986 Award of Merit to Warner by the Conn. League of Historical Societies, and an application submitted to the American Association for State and Local History by William Devlin for a research project entitled Hatter Democracy: A History of Danbury, Connecticut, 1822-1889.
    - Commencement Program, 1985 (Box 34, Folder 49)
    - Miscellaneous, 1983-1992 (Box 34, Folder 50)
      Christmas card, invitations, and programs.
    - William J. Rague, Jr. (Lombok, Indonesia), 1990 (Box 34, Folder 51-54)
      Correspondence, field notes, and research paper entitled The Waktu Lima of Lombok, Indonesia. Newspaper clipping, Faculty Report 1990, and Cooperative Southeast Asian Program.
    - Western Connecticut State University, 1990 (Box 34, Folder 55)
      Class of 1964: 50th reunion program and members' list. (Warner was class advisor)
    - Commencement Marshals Program, 1994 (Box 34, Folder 56)
    - Retirement Speech, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 57)
      Notes for school history talk and retirement speech.
    - Scott Fanton Museum and Historical Society, undated (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence/Notes, 1962-1985 (Box 50, Folder 58-60)
      Membership, elected to Board of Trustees and President, Ives House placed on the National Register of Historic Places, Bicentennial exhibits and events.
    - MSS - Scott Fanton Talk, 1970 (Box 34, Folder 61)
      Manuscript and revisions.
    - Certificate of Gift, 1974-1989 (Box 34, Folder 62-63)
      Gifts to the museum by Warner.
    - Scott Fanton, 1940-1992 (Box 34, Folder 64-66)
      Newspaper articles, Warner becomes president, proposals, membership, and programs. See also: Truman Warner Papers, Scott Fanton Museum.
    - The Mystique of Home Front Sacrifice: Danbury in World War II Exhibit. 1994., undated (Box 34, Folder 67)
      Exhibit booklet (2 copies).
    - Windsor Publications, 1982-1983 (Box 34, Folder 68)
      Correspondence regarding publication of a pictorial history of Danbury with the sponsorship of the Danbury Scott Fanton Museum and Historical Society.
  - 7. Danbury Preservation Trust
    - A River Runs Through It; The Urbanization of Danbury's Still River, 1995-1996 (Box 34, Folder 69-70)
      Exhibit booklet, newspaper articles, and notes. See also: Truman Warner Papers: Historic Preservation; and, Danbury Preservation Trust Records.
    - River Runs Through It; The Urbanization of Danbury's Still River, 1996 (Box OS 7, Folder *)
      Facsimile of The Danbury News Times front page dated August 19, 1955. Two copies.
  - 8. WW II - Letters and Remembrances At Home, 1942-1960